All right. In the last video, I promised
that I'd show you how to make decisions
using code. So, let's actually do that.
Okay. So, the first thing you need to
know when you're making a decision is
you need to know how to compare things.
So, for example, in the decision we
discussed in the last video, my student
looked out the window and said, "If it's
nice outside, in other words, he was
checking what the condition of the
weather was." So, if you're going to
check what a condition is, you need to
make a comparison. So nice outside.
Maybe he was saying, "Is the temperature
greater than 70°?" Um, if it's greater
than 70°, then it's nice outside. Or
maybe he was saying, "If it's partly
cloudy, then it's nice outside." So when
he's making those comparisons, um, in
code, you need to use an operator to
make that comparison. So here are some
of the operators. If you want to
compare, um, to see if something is
exactly the same as something else. So,
in other words, um
someone enters like their password into
a system and you want to check that it's
the right password. You want to say is
the password they entered exactly the
same as the password we're storing. The
way you do that is you'd use a triple
equal sign.
Um if you wanted to see if something was
not equal, then you'd use exclamation
mark and then an equal sign.
Let's say for the case of the weather
that we were talking about, if it's
greater than 70°,
then he would consider it nice outside.
So, you would use the greater than. Um
maybe he's willing to include 70° in his
scale of nice. Um my student that we
referenced in the last video, in that
case, we would use the greater than or
equal to. So, you'd say greater than or
equal to 70°. It's nice outside. Um,
but we know that if it gets greater than
a certain temperature, it's also not so
nice outside. So maybe he was like, and
as long as it's less than 85. So
less than, that's the less than
operator. Um, maybe he's okay if it is
85 exactly. So then he could do a less
than
or equal operator. So these are the
operators we're going to use. Um, in the
next video, we're going to actually
write the if statement. But when you
want to make a comparison between two
variables, you put this between the two
variables.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
create a variable. Let password equal
password. Don't ever make that your
password. U but I'm going to for the
sake of this video. So we'll say let
password equal password. And then I'm
going to prompt
um what is your password?
And I'm going to store that in a
variable. So I need to create a
variable. So I'm going to say let
entered password equal prompt. What is
your password? And then what I'm going
to do is I'm going to alert the result
of comparing password
to the entered password.
So I'm going to save this.
I'm going to go live.
And it says false.
Um I think I must have saved. So what
we're going to do is we're going to
reload this page. Okay. What is your
password? Uh so we're going to say
password. That is the exact password.
And it says true. They are exactly the
same. Um we'll reload the page and we'll
put in something else.
And it says false. So those passwords
were not the same. So, we were able to
use this comparison operator in between
these two um variables to figure out if
they were exactly the same. And then it
returned true or false. So, in this
case, if we entered the right password,
it returned true. If we entered the
wrong password, it returned false. And
we'll take advantage of that in the next